Finding Aid for the Joseph Kaplan Papers LSC.0156
UCLA Library Special Collections
Joseph Kaplan papers
circa 1940-1978
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kaplan, Joseph A.
LSC.0156
1 linear feet (1 oversize box)
Joseph Kaplan (1902- ) was a professof of physics at UCLA, chairman of the department and the director of the Institute of Geophysics. He was also a member of the National Academy of Science, and served as chairman of the U.S. National Committee for the International Geophysical Year (1957-58). The collection consists of framed photographs, files containing clippings, vitae, printed items, manuscripts, and memorabilia.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frances Kaplan, 1992.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9919729573606533
Biography
Kaplan was born in Tapolcza, Hungary on September 8, 1902; arrived in Baltimore, Maryland in 1910; BS in chemistry (1924) and MA (1926) and Ph.D (1927) in physics, Johns Hopkins University; National Research Council fellow at Princeton University (1927-28); assistant professor (1928-35), associate professor (1935-40), then professor, UCLA; chairman, Department of Physics (1938-44); director, Institute of Geophysics (1946-47); research centered on diatomic molecule spectra; nitrogen, oxygen, and mixture afterglows; upper atmosphere chemical processes; member, National Academy of Science; served as chairman of the U.S. National Committee for the International Geophysical Year, 1957-58; wrote Methods and Results of Upper Atmosphere Research (1954).
Scope and Content
Collection consists of materials relating to UCLA physics Professor Joseph Kaplan, including framed photographs, and files containing clippings, vitae, printed items, manuscripts, and memorabilia. Includes report of operations analysis in World War II, The Aeronomy Story, oral history transcript, statement to the House of Representatives Subcommittee on Independent Offices, Early days in Baltimore, and report on International Cooperation in Geographical Research and the Air Force Role in Geophysics.
Manuscripts for publication; Geophysicists -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Kaplan, Joseph, 1902-1991--Archives.; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Physics--Faculty -- Archives
- The Voice of Carelton Alumni, (1957). (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous personal papers []., v.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Operations Analysis in World War II --report., (1947) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence []., v.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- National Research Fellow --notebook., (1927) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Articles and clippings [, v.p.]., v.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photographs. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- International Cooperation in Geographical Research & the Air Force Role in Geophysics --report., (August 1967); 2 copies. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- The Aeronomy Story., Typescript. 2 copies and abstract. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Oral history transcript, (April 1978).; typescript (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Speeches. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Awards and citations. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- International Geophysical Year (1957-1958), [n.d.].; Typescript. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Subcommittee on Independent Offices--House of Representatives--statement to (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Union Geodesique et Geophysique International Association de Meterologie --program with English and French text., (1948) (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Office of Aerospace Research--U.S. Air Force, (1968). (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Early Days in Baltimore--Chapter 1., Holograph manuscript. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Institute of Geophysics and Planetary Sciences, UCLA (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Favorite Professor of UCLA Class of 1942--plaque. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America--award, [1957]. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photographs. (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
- Birthday note from Pol Swings (International Astronomical Union), [n.d.]. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Research Fellow Board--National Research Council--certificate of award, (1927). (Box 2, Folder 7)